Guide to the J.E. Kirkwood Papers 1906-1928
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
J. E. Kirkwood Papers
1906-1928
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 082
Kirkwood, J. E. (Joseph Edward), 1872-1928
0.75 linear feet
Kirkwood was a botanist and professor at the University of Montana. The collection consists of a selection of Kirkwood's published and unpublished writings, mostly on the botany of Montana and Idaho.
Biographical Note
Joseph Edward Kirkwood was born in 1872. He earned his bachelors degree from Pacific University in 1898, a master's from Princeton University in 1902, and a Ph.D. from Columbia University in 1903. He served in many positions in the New York Botanical Garden, the Continental-Mexican Rubber Company, and the Carnegie Institution Desert Laboratory. In 1909, he became a professor of Botany and Forestry at the University of Montana; he became professor of Botany, and head of that department, in 1914. He undertook a trip through the national forests in Montana and Idaho in 1910. Morton J. Elrod provided funding from the budget of the University of Montana Biological Station on Flathead Lake. Kirkwood died in 1928.
The collection consists of a selection of Kirkwood's published and unpublished writings, mostly on the botany of Montana and Idaho. Particular areas of focus are the Selway and Flathead rivers and the Coeur d'Alene, Kaniksu, and Lolo national forests. One manuscript provides insight into the national forests and fire control policies during the summer of 1910. He moved around the region by train, stage, saddle horse, and on foot, and so provides insight into travel conditions. His published writings appeared in a variety of regional and national publications, including Northwest Science, National Geographic, The Scientific Monthly, and The Journal of Home Economics.
The collection is divided into two series:
Series I: Writings, 0.5 linear feet, 1910-1928
Series II: Publications, 0.25 linear feet, 1906-1928
Notes on Observations in National Forests and Elsewhere During the Summer of 1910 is also available on microfilm.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Gift of Mary Kirkwood, 1983.
Duplicate copies of publications were discarded.
Botanists -- Montana
Botany--Idaho; Botany--Montana; Forest fires--Montana -- 1910; Forest reserves -- Idaho; Forest reserves -- Montana
Coeur d'Alene National Forest (Idaho); Flathead River Valley (B.C. and Mont.); Idaho--Description and travel; Kaniksu National Forest; Lolo National Forest (Mont.); Montana--Description and travel; Selway-Bitterroot Wilderness (Idaho and Mont.)
University of Montana -- Missoula--Faculty
Montana; Idaho; Environmental Conditions; Forestry and Forestry Products; Science
- Writings, circa 1910-1928; Series I; 0.5 linear feet
  This Series includes the original typescripts for a number of Kirkwood's publications. The writings all relate to the botany of the Rocky Mountains of Montana and Idaho, particularly that of the Selway River, the South Fork of the Flathead River, and the Coeur d'Alene, Kaniksu, and Lolo forests in Montana and Idaho. The manuscript titled Notes on Observations in National Forests and Elsewhere During the Summer of 1910 includes photographs and commentary on United States Forest Service policies. One undated radio address also describes and promotes the Department of Botany at the University of Montana. One paper appears to be the work of a student named Kirk Robertson, not Kirkwood.
  The materials are arranged chronologically.
  - "Notes on Observations in National Forests and Elsewhere During the Summer of 1910", circa 1910 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - "Botanical Explorations in the Rocky Mountains: The Selway", circa 1925 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - "Botanical Explorations in the Rocky Mountains: The South Fork of the Flathead", circa 1927 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - "Botanical Explorations in the Rocky Mountains: The Lolo Trail", circa 1928 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - "Report of the Committee on Larger Opportunities and Facilities for Research and Publication", undated (Box-folder 1/5)
  - "The Department of Botany of the State University of Montana" (radio address), undated (Box-folder 1/6)
  - "Some Conspicuous Families of Rocky Mountain Plants", undated (Box-folder 1/7)
  - "Trees and Shrubs of the Northern Rocky Mountains", undated (Box-folder 1/8)
  - "The Birch Family (Betulaceae)", undated (Box-folder 1/9)
  - "The Heath Family (Ericaceae)", undated (Box-folder 1/10)
  - "Delgado's Ride" (by Kirk Robertson), undated (Box-folder 1/11)
- Publications, 1906-1928; Series II; 0.25 linear feet
  This series includes articles published by Kirkwood. Most of the articles are reprints. Many of the articles focus on the Rocky Mountain area, but a few articles discuss tropical botany and the importance of teaching botany.
  - "The Pollen-Tube In Some of the Cucurbitaceae," Bulletin of the Torrey Botanical Club, 1906 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - "Some Features of Pollen-Formation In the Cucurbitaceae," Bulletin of the Torrey Botanical Club, 1907 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - "The Propagation of Guayule By Seed," American Review of Tropical Agriculture, 1910 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - "The Growth of Guayule In Relation to the Soil," The American Review of Tropical Agriculture, 1910 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - "A Mexican Hacienda," National Geographic Magazine, May 1914 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - "Peridermium Pyriforme and Cronartium Comandrae," Phytopathology, August 1915 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - "Bisporangiate Cones of Larix," Botanical Gazette, March 1916 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - "The Practical In Education," The Inter-Mountain Educator, January 1918 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - "Opportunity and Obligation In Botanical Teaching," School Science and Mathematics, 1918 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - "The Case of General Science," Education, November 1919 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - "Botanical Instruction For Students of Home Economics," The Journal of Home Economics, July 1922 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - "Botany of the Rocky Mountains," Torreya, November-December 1926 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - "Botanical Field Work in Montana," Address to the Chi Chapter of Phi Sigma, February 11, 1927 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - "Botany In High School and College," School Science and Mathematics, December 1927 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - "Botanical Explorations In the Rocky Mountains - Selway River," The Scientific Monthly, December 1927 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - "Botanical Explorations In the Rocky Mountains - The Lolo Trail," The Scientific Monthly, April 1928 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - "Notes on Some Forest Seeding Experiments in the Rocky Mountains," Northwest Science, undated (Box-folder 2/17)